Guide to the Ruth Crawford Mitchell Papers, 1914-1980 UA.90.F12
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ruth Crawford Mitchell Papers
1914-1980
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Mitchell, Ruth Crawford
UA.90.F12
12.5 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
The papers of Ruth Crawford Mitchell consist primarily of documents related to the Nativity Study carried out by the University of Pittsburgh between 1926 and 1930. The Nativity Study collected information on foreign-born and first generation American students applying to the university in an attempt to provide better services for them. The collection also contains information on a study of second generation foreign students, a Civil Affairs Training Program, immigration, countries and ethnic groups, lecture notes for Ms. Mitchell's classes, and her personal papers.
Biography
Ruth Crawford Mitchell was born on June 2, 1890 in Atlantic Heights, New Jersey. She earned a Bachelor of Arts degree from Vassar College, and a Master of Arts from Washington University with a thesis entitled "The Immigrant in St. Louis."
After graduating from Washington University, Mitchell became the Field Secretary for the Immigration and Foreign Community Program of the YWCA in 1914. In this position, Mitchell was responsible for establishing and staffing centers to help immigrant women adjust to life in the United States. When the United States entered World War I, she organized "hostess houses." These houses, staffed with women who spoke foreign languages, were designed to help foreign-born soldiers in the United States army.
In 1924, Mitchell came to the University of Pittsburgh where she worked as a lecturer in the Department of Economics. After becoming interested in her students' ethnic backgrounds, she chaired a project to learn more about the nativity of Pitt students. Over a four-year period, Mitchell collected information on students applying for admission and their family background. This information was used in budget requests in an attempt to provide better services to foreign-born students. The data showed similarities in the percentage of foreign students at the University of Pittsburgh to the number of foreign residents in Allegheny County.
After the Nativity Study was completed, Chancellor John C. Bowman asked Mitchell to assist in the design of classrooms for the Cathedral of Learning. Mitchell assisted in bringing together different ethnic groups, reflecting the various nationalities of people helping to build Pittsburgh and Allegheny County. A total of 19 different Nationality Rooms were constructed between 1938 and 1957.
Mitchell remained at Pitt until 1956, with a hiatus from 1944-1946 to serve with the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Agency in Egypt. She retired in 1956 as Director Emerita of the Nationality Rooms and Intercultural Exchange Program. During her career, Mitchell received many awards, including Doctor of Humanities Honoris Causa, and the Chancellor's Medal, both from the University of Pittsburgh. Mitchell died on February 4, 1984 and is buried in Pepperell, Massachusetts.
Scope and Content Notes
The papers of Ruth Crawford Mitchell center primarily on her life-long interest in immigrants in the United States. This arises in the collection in the form of two studies, one on second-generation students of foreign descent and another on the nativity of Pitt students. The Nativity Study takes up the bulk of the collection and includes the three bound volumes which make up the summary of the study. The remainder of the Nativity Study includes reports, raw data, tables and information on individual students. Also included is information about the students' families, including such information as father's country of origin, native language, occupation and the family's religion. Similar information was collected on second-generation students, though the information is not in as great detail as the Nativity Study.
The remainder of the collection consists of personal papers, information about immigration, different countries and ethnic groups, and Mitchell's work as a lecturer in the Department of Economics. Information on a course for military personnel on civil affairs training also makes up a series in the collection. The final series in the collection contains information on the Pittsburgh Pact, which details the meeting and agreement which led to the merger of the Czech Republic and Slovakia.
Access Restrictions
Series VI contains student files and therefore the contents are restricted. Researchers must sign a confidentiality agreement in order to have access.
Acquisition Information
Accessioned August 15, 1968.
Previous Citation
Ruth Crawford Mitchell Papers, 1914-1980, UA.90.F12, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
United States -- Emigration and immigration; Faculty papers; Czecho-Slovak pact (1918 May 30: Pittsburgh, Pa.); Children of immigrants -- Education -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Children of immigrants -- Education -- United States; University of Pittsburgh; Mitchell, Ruth Crawford
- Economics and History of Immigration Courses, 1926-1927; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains the lecture notes for Mitchell's Economics 9 and 10 courses and her History of Immigration course. These courses were taught in 1926 and 1927. The majority of the folders in this series contain articles and lecture notes. Series I also contains information on the Civil Affairs Specialist Training Program, which was held at Pitt in 1943. This program taught military personnel about foreign languages and customs.
  - History of Immigration (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and class (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Case histories of immigrants (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Assimilation course (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lecture notes and articles on nationality and language (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lecture notes on prehistoric man and migrations (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lecture notes re: immigration 1882-1918; extracts of articles on immigrants; lecture notes for period 1918-24. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lecture notes on international aspects of immigration (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Restrictive immigration to the U.S. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Student reactions to course on History of Immigration. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Outline and lecture notes for nationality courses (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Civil Affairs Specialist Training Program (Box 1, Folder 12)
- The Pittsburgh Pact and Czechoslovakian History, 1928-1960; II.
  Series II concerns the Pittsburgh Pact and the role Pittsburgh played in Czechoslovakian History. The Pact was a paper drawn up in Pittsburgh in 1918 by representatives of Slovak and Czech organizations in the United States, including the Slovak League, the Czech National Alliance and the Alliance of Czech Nationalities in the presence of Thomas Masaryk, Chairman of the Czecho-Slovak National Council. He was later President of Czechoslovakia. The series contains copies of the pact as well as information on the role Pittsburgh played in bringing the Czech Republic and Slovakia together.
  - Copy in Czech and English of the wording of the pact. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Journal articles. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Typescripts of articles on the Pittsburgh Pact and Czechoslovakia. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence and memoranda regarding the Pact and the establishment of Czechoslovakia. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mitchell's handwritten notes (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence and manuscripts. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Personal Papers, 1914-1980; III.
  Series III concerns Mitchell's personal papers. These papers include ten photographic albums, and a notebook of her expectations for her household staff. The series includes Mitchell's notes and a copy of her book on Alice Carrigue Masaryk as well as two of her diaries.
  - Chancellor's medal citation. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Program for dinner honoring Ruth C. Mitchell. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Phi Beta Kappa certificate presented to Ruth Mitchell. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Citation by UNRRA. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Conferring of Honorary Degree - Doctor of Humanities. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Citation presented when leaving first job at national YMCA and correspondence. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Citations and awards. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Yearbook, transcript, and correspondence. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Publications. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Ruth C. Mitchell Diary, February-June 1919 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Ruth C. Mitchell Diary, July-September 1919 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Ruth C. Mitchell Masaryk Materials (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Photo album, hand bound leather with personal pictures, 1952-1983 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - J.B. Priestley, Delight. New York: Harper Brothers, 1949. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Robert Bridges. The Spirit of Man. New York: Longmans Green Co., 1919. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Ruth Crawford Mitchell. Alice Carrigue Masaryk, 1879-1966. Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1979. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Report of the Commission on First Generation Americans - Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 34a)
- Immigration, 1920-1940; IV.
  Series IV concerns immigration to the United States during the 1920s, 1930s and 1940s. Included in the series is a notebook Mitchell compiled at an international immigration conference and a notebook for her lectures on immigration. The scrapbooks listed under FF 37 through FF 39 contain articles on immigrants clipped from newspapers.
  - Census - United States Population 1920 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Census - United States Population, 1930 1940 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Scrapbook (Box 2, Volume 37)
  - Scrapbook (Box 2, Volume 38)
  - Scrapbook (Box 2, Volume 39)
- Countries and Nationalities, 1914-1930; V.
  Series V concerns various countries and ethnic groups. Mitchell was an avid reader and often kept articles concerning foreign countries and their citizens. The folders in this series, organized alphabetically by country, contain articles, pamphlets, papers and correspondence about these different places and groups.
  - Armenia - General (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Canada-General (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - China (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - China - General (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - China - Manchuria (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Croatia - General (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Czechs - General Characteristics (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Czechoslovakia (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Czechoslovak (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Europe - Central (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Foreign Language Publications - USA (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Greek - General (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Italy - General (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Japan - General (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Jewish Nationality Group - General (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Lithuania - General (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Hungary (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Hungary Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Hungary - Notes (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Hungary (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Mexico - General (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Near East (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Norway - General (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Poland - General (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Roumania - General (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Russia - General (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Scandinavian Countries (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Serbia - General (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Slovenia - General (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Jugoslav (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Yugoslavia - General (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Slovak - General (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Slovak Department in American Institute in Prague (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Sweden - General (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Syria - General (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Ukrainia - General (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Ukrania - Notes (Box 3, Folder 76)
- Nativity Study [RESTRICTED], 1926-1930; VI.
  Series VI contains information regarding the Nativity Study carried out at the University of Pittsburgh between 1926 and 1930. This was an attempt by the University to gain a better understanding of the number of foreign-born and first-generation students and find better ways to meet their needs. Three other universities - the University of Buffalo, Yale University and the University of Chicago - also conducted similar studies. Included in the series are three bound volumes which make up the final report of the study. The study includes reports on students' home backgrounds and information on individual students who took part in the study. This information includes data on the students and their families, immigration status and academic performance. Data on psychological testing for five students is included, as are reports on immigration law as it applied to foreign students.
  Access to the contents of this series requires a signed confidentiality agreement on behalf of the researcher.
  - University of Buffalo (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Write Up Material for Second Generation Student Study, University of Buffalo (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Write up material, Yale University (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Second Generation Students, Committee on, YWCA, 1929-30 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Write up material for second generation student study - General University Opinion (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - University of New York (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - YWCA Committee on the Second Generation Girl (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Other University Material (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Nativity Study - 1933 - Extra Finished Tables (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Foreign Born and Second Generation Students, Misc. Tables, Unfinished (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Cathedral of Learning, Colored Students (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - General University of Pittsburgh Material (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Foreign Student - Personnel Card (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Second Generation Students Italian Descent List, 1928-29 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Second Generation Students German Descent List, 1928-29 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Gow, J. Steele; Committee on Foreign Students (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Second Generation Student Lists; Student Study - 1929-30 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Second Generation Student Lists; Student Study - 1929-30 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Original Tables; Student Study -1929-30 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Complete Set of Tables, Student Studies, 1929-30 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Complete Set of Comparative Tables, Student Study, 1926-30 (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Original Tables, Comparative Study, 1926-30 (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Nativity Studies, U of P, Yale and Buffalo, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Procedure in Compilation of Data (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - Write Up Materials for Second Generation Student Study - Statistical Study - Carnegie Tests - Bureau of Research Higher Education, June 1930 (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Recommended Program for 1930-31 (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Nativity Study Bibliography, Sections 1-4 (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - Nativity Study - First Annual Report (Box 4, Folder 105)
  - Nativity Study - Second Annual Report (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Nativity Study - Third Annual Report (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - Nativity Study - Fourth Annual Report, Part I (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Nativity Study - Fourth Annual Report, Part II (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Nativity Study - Table 4 - Yale (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - Ellis, Mabel Brown - Report on a Study of Home Backgrounds Made for the University of Pittsburgh, May 1928 (Box 4, Folder 111)
  - Ellis, Mabel Brown - Report on a Study of Home Backgrounds Made for the University of Pittsburgh, May 1928 (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Ellis, Mabel Brown - Report on a Study of Home Backgrounds Made for the University of Pittsburgh, April 1928 (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Ellis, Mabel Brown - Report on a Study of Home Backgrounds Made for the University of Pittsburgh, April 1928 (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - Papers and Photos Removed from Cardfile: "Foreign Student Immigration Status," Nativity Study (Box 4, Folder 115)
  - Foreign Students - Lists 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - Foreign Students - Prospective (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Bulletin (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Admission Procedure, History of (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Appointments by Mr. Gow, 1929-30 (Box 5, Folder 120)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Auxiliary Committee 1928-29 (Box 5, Folder 121)
  - Foreign Students, Statistics 1932 (Box 5, Folder 122)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Basis of Classification (Box 5, Folder 123)
  - Foreign Visitors for C.O.F.S. (Box 5, Folder 124)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Foreign Guests of the University of Pittsburgh (Box 5, Folder 125)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Government Reports 1930 (Box 5, Folder 126)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Government Reports 1927-28-29 (Box 5, Folder 127)
  - Committee on Foreign Students, History of Organization (Box 5, Folder 128)
  - Committee on Foreign Students Lists (Box 5, Folder 129)
  - Committee on Foreign Students Minutes 1928-29 (Box 5, Folder 130)
  - Committee on Foreign Students Minutes 1929-30 (Box 5, Folder 131)
  - Committee on Foreign Students Minutes 1930-31 (Box 5, Folder 132)
  - Committee on Foreign Students Pamphlet (Box 5, Folder 133)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Personnel Record Reports (Box 5, Folder 134)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Mr. Quick - General (Box 5, Folder 135)
  - Committee on Foreign Students Report 1929-30 (Box 5, Folder 136)
  - Committee on Foreign Students Report 1928-29 (Box 5, Folder 137)
  - Committee on Foreign Students Reports - 1926-27 and 1927-28 (Box 5, Folder 138)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Current Discussions (Box 5, Folder 139)
  - Lai, Chi Fang (Box 5, Folder 140)
  - Foreign Students: Inactive - L (Box 5, Folder 141)
  - Foreign Students: Inactive File - J-K (Box 5, Folder 142)
  - Foreign Students: Inactive - M-N (Box 5, Folder 143)
  - Foreign Students: Inactive - P-S (Box 5, Folder 144)
  - Foreign Students: Inactive - V-Z (Box 5, Folder 145)
  - Foreign Students: Student Files - A-B (Box 5, Folder 146)
  - Foreign Students: Student Files - C-D (Box 5, Folder 147)
  - Foreign Students: Student Files - E-G (Box 5, Folder 148)
  - Foreign Students: Student Files - H-M (Box 5, Folder 149)
  - Foreign Students: Student Files - N-P (Box 6, Folder 150)
  - Foreign Students: Student Files - R-T (Box 6, Folder 151)
  - Foreign Students: Student Files - U-Z (Box 6, Folder 152)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Foreign Fellowships, 1929-30 (Box 6, Folder 153)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Foreign Fellowships, 1928-29 (Box 6, Folder 154)
  - Committee on Foreign Students - Foreign Fellowships, 1927-28 (Box 6, Folder 155)
  - Institutue of International Education Foreign Representatives on International Student Exchange Activities (Box 6, Folder 156)
  - Exchange Fellowships - Czechoslovakian (Box 6, Folder 157)
  - Exchange Fellowships - Swiss (Box 6, Folder 158)
  - Exchange Fellowships - French (Box 6, Folder 159)
  - Exchange Fellowships - German (Box 6, Folder 160)
  - Exchange Fellowships - Italian (Box 6, Folder 161)
  - Committee on Foreign Students: Credentials of Applicants for University - Foreign Fellowship, 1931-32 (Box 6, Folder 162)
  - Committee on Foreign Students: Credentials of Applicants for University - Foreign Fellowship, 1930-31 (Box 6, Folder 163)
  - Committee on Foreign Students: Committee on Foreign Study (Box 6, Folder 164)
  - Foreign Students - Miscellaneous Material (Box 6, Folder 165)
  - White-Williams Foundation (Box 6, Folder 166)
  - Kosciuszko Foundation (Box 6, Folder 167)
  - Foreign Students - Faculty Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 168)
  - Foreign Students - Expenses, Average Monthly (Box 6, Folder 169)
  - Frick Commission (Box 6, Folder 170)
  - School of Slavonic Studies (Box 6, Folder 171)
  - Morsbach, Dr. Adolph (Box 6, Folder 172)
  - Institute of International Education: 1930-31 Lecturers (Box 6, Folder 173)
  - English FX - English for Foreigners (Box 6, Folder 174)
  - Foreign Students: Bureau of Business Research Fellowship (Box 6, Folder 175)
  - Guidebook on German Universities for Foreign Students (Box 6, Folder 176)
  - Requests for Scholarship Aid: 1929-30 (Box 6, Folder 177)
  - Committee on Foreign Students: Procedure for Award of Foreign Fellowship (Box 6, Folder 178)
  - Foreign Fellowship Procedure (Box 6, Folder 179)
  - Committee on Foreign Fellowships: Foreign Fellowships 1931-32 (Box 6, Folder 180)
  - Committee on Foreign Students: University Foreign Fellowships, 1930-31 (Box 6, Folder 181)
  - Foreign Students - Alien Declarants (Box 6, Folder 182)
  - Foreign Students - Alien Residents (Box 6, Folder 183)
  - Foreign Students - Exclusions and Deportations (Box 6, Folder 184)
  - Foreign Students - Exclusions and Deportations (Box 6, Folder 185)
  - Foreign Students - Left University, Right of Residence (Box 6, Folder 186)
  - Foreign Students - Naturalized Citizens (Box 6, Folder 187)
  - Committee on Foreign Students: Admissions Procedure, Printed and Current Material (Box 6, Folder 188)
  - Foreign Students and U.S. Immigration Law, article for Educational Record (Box 6, Folder 189)
  - Committee on Foreign Students Educational Institutions approved by the Secretary of Labor (Box 6, Folder 190)
  - Czmar, Derso Erno (Box 6, Folder 191)
  - D'Ambry, Guy L. (Box 6, Folder 192)
  - de Villiers, Ignatius (Box 6, Folder 193)
  - Dukic, Mirko (Box 6, Folder 194)
  - Genca, Giacomo (Box 6, Folder 195)
  - Hershtenkorn, Meir (Box 6, Folder 196)
  - Lee, Yao (Box 6, Folder 197)
  - Mihoylitcheuko, Victor Basil (Box 7, Folder 198)
  - Nagroth, Giand Chand (Box 7, Folder 199)
  - Warner, Maglalena (Box 7, Folder 200)
  - Pappadato, Olga Yagodkin (Box 7, Folder 201)
  - Russell, R.S. (Box 7, Folder 202)
  - Stadnichenko, Vladimir M. (Box 7, Folder 203)
  - Camaroff, Rachel (Box 7, Folder 204)
  - del Valle, Luis (Box 7, Folder 205)
  - Idovich, Iser (Box 7, Folder 206)
  - Manduca, Domenico (Box 7, Folder 207)
  - Neszaros, Joseph (Box 7, Folder 208)
  - Marabito, Letterio (Box 7, Folder 209)
  - Nudelman, Gerc (Box 7, Folder 210)
  - Salate, Lazar (Box 7, Folder 211)
  - Siposs, Stephen (Box 7, Folder 212)
  - Uppal, B.N. (Box 7, Folder 213)
  - Interpretation of the U.S. Immigration Laws; Official Governmental; Private of Social Agencies (Box 7, Folder 214)
  - Committee on Foreign Students: Official Interpretation of Section 4 (e) (Box 7, Folder 215)
  - Committee on Foreign Students: Letters Concerning Future (Box 7, Folder 216)
  - Committee on Foreign Students: Speech Materials, Supervision of 4 (e) Students (Box 7, Folder 217)
  - Foreign Students and the United States Immigration Law, Report on (Box 7, Folder 218)
  - Foreign Students and the U.S. Immigration Law; Report by Ruth Crawford Mitchell - Mailing Lists (Box 7, Folder 219)
  - Foreign Students, Clippings (Box 7, Folder 220)
  - Foreign Students: Conference on Students Under The Immigration Law - Institute of International Education (Box 7, Folder 221)
  - Foreign Students: Court Decisions Concerning (Box 7, Folder 222)
  - Foreign Students - Dinner to Meet Chancellor Bowman, December 1930 (Box 7, Folder 223)
  - Foreign Students - Dinner to Meet Chancellor, October 15, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 224)
  - Foreign Students - Dinner to Meet Chancellor, Oct. 11, 1927 Oct. 9, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 225)
  - Foreign Students - Hospitality (Box 7, Folder 226)
  - Foreign Students - Lists 1932-33 (Box 7, Folder 227)
  - Foreign Students - Lists 1931-32 (Box 7, Folder 228)
  - Foreign Students - Lists 1930-31 (Box 7, Folder 229)
  - Foreign Students - Lists 1929-30 (Box 7, Folder 230)
  - Foreign Students - Lists 1928-29 (Box 7, Folder 231)
  - Foreign Students and the United States Immigration Laws; Ruth Crawford Mitchell, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pa., June, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 232)
  - Foreign Students and the United States Immigration Laws; Ruth Crawford Mitchell, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pa., June, 1928, (Technical Revision) (Box 7, Folder 233)